Guide to the Houston National Bank Records
University of Houston Libraries
Houston National Bank Records
1889-1964
1930-1955
1969-075
Houston National Bank (Houston, Tex.)
4.00 Linear Feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection includes administrative files from the Houston National Bank, as well as scrapbooks of prominent individuals associated with the bank.
Historical Note:
The Houston National Bank was founded in 1876 as a private bank by Henry S. Fox, Sr., who served as the bank's president until his death in 1912. Cofounder Joseph F. Meyers, Sr. succeeded him as president until Henry S. Fox, Jr. assumed the bank's presidency from 1914 until 1925. In 1928, Houston National Bank moved its headquarters into a newly-constructed building on the southwest corner of Main and Franklin Streets in downtown Houston.
Beginning in 1931, Joseph F. Meyer, Jr. served as president until the bank sold a substantial portion of its stock in 1950 to a group of businessmen, including the President of the Gulftex Drug Company, Irvin M. Shlenker, and longtime Houston National Bank employee Melvin Rouff, who was subsequently made president. The Houston National Bank merged with the Tennessee Bank and Trust Company in 1964.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Administrative records; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Ephemera; Pamphlets; Personal papers; Programs (documents); Scrapbooks
Topical Term:
Bankers -- Texas -- Houston; Banks and banking -- Texas -- Houston
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes administrative files from the Houston National Bank, as well as scrapbooks of prominent individuals associated with the bank.
The administrative files primarily pertain to the bank's 75th anniversary, celebrated in 1951. These files include correspondence, promotional material, photographs, pamphlets, and newspaper clippings. The administrative files also include publicity files and materials documenting organizations and conventions associated with the Texas Bankers Association.
The collection also includes personal papers from individuals associated with the bank, including the bank's president Melvin Rouff. Three scrapbooks containing correspondence, photographs, and newspaper clippings pertaining to banking comprise the personal papers.
Detailed List of Contents
- Administrative Records
  Scope and Contents
  The administrative records primarily pertain to the bank's 75th and 85th anniversaries, which were celebrated in 1951 and 1961. These files include correspondence, promotional material, photographs, pamphlets, and newspaper clippings. The records also include publicity files, which contain three scrapbooks with newspaper clippings of advertising campaign materials, as well as a campaign book for the bank's "Landmarks That Live" campaign. The organizations and conventions materials consist of a large scrapbook containing materials pertaining to the 48th and 49th annual conventions for the Texas Bankers Association.
  - Anniversary Celebrations
    - Administrative files, 1889-1894, 1939-1964, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Pamphlets, 1927, 1953, 1961, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Postcards and stamps, 1951, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Newspapers, 1876, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Newspapers, 1916, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Newspapers, 1951-1956, 1962, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Publicity
    - Scrapbook, 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Scrapbook, 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Scrapbook, 1925-1928 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Scrapbook, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Scrapbook, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "Landmarks That Live" campaign book, 1951, 1953, undated (Ovs box 1, Folder 1)
  - Organizations and Conventions
    - Scrapbook with 48th and 49th annual convention programs and publications for the Texas Bankers Association, 1932-1933 (Box 1, Folder 13-18)
- Personal Papers
  The personal papers document the activities of individuals associated with the bank, including the bank's president, Melvin Rouff. Three scrapbooks containing correspondence, photographs, and newspaper clippings pertaining to banking comprise the personal papers.
  - Scrapbook labeled "Emma Goldberg," with a variety of early Houston bank advertisements from Houston National Bank and others, 1910, 1930, 1956, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Memory book of Melvin Rouff scrapbook, 1927-1931, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-4)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1938, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Items removed from Melvin Rouff ship scrapbook
  - Postcards, 1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1933-1949, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Photographs, 1939, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Programs, 1936-1950 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook of Melvin Rouff with ship cover, 1936-1939 (Ovs box 1, Folder 2)